hey what's up guys my name is Archana
welcome back to my staples loss series
today we're gonna be talking all about
how you can set up multiple projects in
Visual Studio and how you can create a
library that you can use in all of your
projects so this is something that's
really important if you're working on
anything kind of sizable not only does
it help you to create a module or a
library with your code and reuse that
code multiple times but it also lets you
mix languages and that's something that
might be important to you if again
you're working on something fairly large
so today we're just gonna stick with C++
and we're gonna talk about how you can
basically create one project that is
compiled as a library as specifically a
static library and then link that into
an executable and how that all kind of
works in a visual studio so let's take a
look so here I'm just starting with a
completely empty folder because a folder
called C++ and it's going to contain all
these projects of money back in Visual
Studio I'm just going to go over here
and select file new project so I'm going
to be setting up a brand new solution
which will contain my multiple projects
so I already here on the templates and
visual C++ I'm just gonna just like
general and an empty project and then
I'm going to give this a name now I'm
gonna call this game you'll notice
that's also the solution name and I'm
also going to make sure the crate
directory for solution is checked now
I'll call this game because it's gonna
be like a game project our actual
executable and then I'm going to make a
library called engine inside there which
links into game and you'll see that in a
minute so click OK here set the visual
studio creates our solution and project
and you can see that we both solution
called game and a project called game as
well if I go back to Windows Explorer
and take a look at that directory
structure I've got game and then I've
got a solution file here and then inside
another folder called game I've got my
actual C++ project you guys will know a
little bit more about the structure of
Visual Studio C++ projects and how to
set them up better I've made a video
directly about that called the best way
to set up your sleep uh suppose projects
and visual studios in the top right
corner check it out okay so that's
pretty good to me we've got our first
project now let's go ahead and add
another project I'm going to right click
on this solution here select add and
then new project now again I like to set
up my C++ projects just as empty project
so that's all I'm going to do I'm going
to select empty project here I'm going
to give it the name engine and
I'm going to click ok so now if I
collapse all of this you can see that
our solution has two projects engine and
game game is going to be our executable
if we right click and hit properties
which is going to make sure that under
the game property pages our
configuration type under the duration
properties in general is set to
application okay that's that's final
I'll click OK and then let's take a look
at engine I'll right click on engine hit
properties and then for this since we
are going to be linking statically I'm
going to make sure that my configuration
type is set to static library and that's
all that we need to do to make this a
static library for the most part again
I'm just making sure that I'm modifying
this for all configurations and even for
all platforms as well so I'm going to
just not save the changes here and make
sure that for all configurations and all
platforms I'm setting this to be a
static library I'm going to hit OK and
then now let's write some code to test
this out so what I'm going to do is just
show all files here for both of these
projects so that I can actually make my
sauce directories right click add new
folder source contributors for both of
the projects and game is going to get a
application door CPP file which is going
to be basically the source of our
application I guess will be the main
file and on the engine I'm just going to
make a new item it's going to be a
header file and I'm going to call this
image piece over here I'm going to call
this engine H and I'm also going to make
a C++ file it's going to be called
engine Dulce TP ok cool and for this
incredibly basics test I'm just going to
write name space engine and then on the
here void print message and not going to
take any parameters or anything like
that I'm going to leave this
unimplemented because I'm going to go to
the C++ file include my engine dot H
header file right name space engine and
then implement that print message
function here and I'm just gonna make it
print hello world to the console I'm
also going to make sure that in the C++
file I include iostream so that we can
print that ok cool so very very basic
there's my header file there's my sleep
locals file we're not even dealing with
classes or anything like that to now
just really really simple we just got
one function in our engine so back an
application built CPP my goal here as I
write
this little main function of mine my
goal here is basically to just be able
to call engine print message I want to
be able to write this card I wanted to
be able to execute the link successfully
and all that right into my executable
how do I do that so the first step is I
need to include a header file which
defines this I don't technically
speaking need to do this like in this
case because it's so simple I could
literally write a namespace engine and
then void print message and of course
like that's it you can see that that
error goes away if I try and compile my
code but by pressing control f7 you can
see over here that it does in fact
compiled successfully of course it's not
going to link because I don't actually
have a definition to this so if I build
this all the way it's not going on
without we're gonna get a linking error
however you kind of get the point now
this code is exactly what is in my
engine - right so of course instead of
using my own kind of solution here my
own version of this we want to be using
this actual header file so how do we do
that
well all we need to do is include that
actual header file that is inside our
engine project there's a few ways we
could do this I'll show you a couple so
one way is just relative to this current
path so application does leave it be if
I right-click on this actual tab and
click open containing folder because the
application of CPP is inside game game
and their source so if I go back one
directory and then another directory I
can theoretically go into engine source
and then engine I so what I could do
with an include is just go back to
directories go into engine source and
then engine dilash and you can see there
we go our error goes away and we can
compile our coach is fine now obviously
this is just not not ideal at all I mean
we have a relative path that is going
back to directories and then into an
entirely different project in the source
it looks very messy and if we move
folders or rename the name of the
project or something like that
everything's gonna break so what we
actually want to do is use absolute
paths and specifically using compiler
include paths so let's take a look at
what that looks like so instead of this
I'm going to right-click on game go to
properties and then under C C++ in
general as an additional include
directory I'm going to include that
engine source directory which is over
here this engine source directory and
I'm going to do that by typing in dollar
sign that's
solution directory engine which is the
aim of the project and then backslash
source right that is my include
directory if I expand this and click
edit you can see that it evaluates to
that James slash engine slash source
directory right solution directory is
just a macro which expands to be
location or specifically the directory
of that solution file so in other words
the directory that contains this dot SLN
file that's what that solution directory
macro is and if we add on the name of
the project and then source we get there
so now what I can do inside this
application the CPP file is instead of
including that massive like relative
path here I can just replace this with a
path that is relative to my actual
source directory inside engines so in
this case that's going to end up just
being engine dot H like that and that's
all I need to do right and I can get rid
of that other one and hit ctrl f7 you
can see compositors fine now because
we've specified it as a compiler include
path I could also replace these quotes
with angular brackets like this and some
people may prefer to do this personally
I don't I use angular brackets if I'm
including something that is outside of
this visual studio solution so something
that is an external dependency in
completely external to the project if
the code for this engine dot H file is
actually found inside this solution or
specifically something written by me
inside this solution not something like
this a bus bus standard library then I
will use quotes to indicate that this is
kind of one of our source files so I'm
going to bring back those quotes ok
fantastic so we've got our header files
all included now everything's working
great but project isn't linking because
we're not actually linking to the
library so there's a few things there's
a few ways that we could actually do
that first of all you need to understand
what happens to the library if I
right-click on my engine and hit build
you can see that what Visual Studio does
is it generates this Lib file and if we
actually go to the path that it
specifies over here then you can see we
have this live file this is what we want
to actually link against now what we
could do if you watch my video on static
linking which is linked over there we
could just kind of go to our linker
settings and put that in as an input but
we don't have to do that Visual Studio
can actually kind of automate this for
us because this project is in the App
solution so what we can do is actually
right-click on game here add and then
reference and then we can select inside
our projects and solution we can select
this engine project and then just click
OK now this is basically going to link
in that live file into our executable as
if we had added it to the linker input
but this also gives us another advantage
apart from not having to kind of deal
with setting up an actual file name
because obviously if we change the name
of engine to call or something like that
if it's now called core we have to go
back to our linker settings for game and
actually change the input to be court
live instead of engine the little Lib
and if we use a reference like this we
don't have to do that that's all
automated but apart from that I'm not
even talking about that another benefit
is engine is now a dependency again so
game depends on engine meaning that if
something inside engine changes and we
go to compile game game is actually
going to compile engine and game so we
know that we're dealing always with the
most up-to-date code there's never a
chance that oh wait I forgot to compile
engine that's why this isn't working or
something like that it's all kind of
handled automatically it creates like a
full dependency graph for us so
everything works really nicely so now
back in our code I'll even prove this by
just right clicking here and clicking
clean solution you'll know that I'm just
going to go to game and build game but
you can see that what it actually does
is build engine first and then game
because engine is actually required for
game to work since we've added it as a
reference and since we're linking
against it back here in our turn I'm
just going to add a cm get I'll have to
include iostream to make that happen
this is just to pause the console so
that we don't quit straightaway and now
I'm going to run my application and you
can see that HelloWorld gets printed at
the console and everything seems to work
successfully so that's it I hope you
guys enjoyed the video this was just
about static linking in the future we
might I might do a video that's
specifically about this but with dynamic
linking because it is a little bit
different and there are some things that
you need to be aware of but generally
again I will link statically in fact if
we go back to our code real quick what's
happened now is even though we've had
those two projects if I go into my
solution directory debug you can see
that there's just game don't you see if
I take that game don't yet see and I'll
open two completely different folder
here called dist
which is on my desktop I'll paste it in
here that's all I need to actually run
this program if I double click on this
ax a file you can see it's going to run
my program and that's it because we're
linking statically so everything gets
put into that exe file there's no actual
external file dependency gangully ACC
has everything we want so we've managed
to successfully link statically and
still kind of have multiple projects in
visual studio now this is very useful
because again if we were actually
building a game engine we might have
this like this this solution might have
several examples of how to use the
engine or several games or something
like that that all reference that one
engine file that one engine project so
that's why we kind of what we kind of
want to modularize this so that we have
all about kind of core code or
centralized in one project and then we
can just you know have all of our
examples or all of our actual
applications our executables linked
against that one centralized project
hope you guys enjoyed this video if you
did you hit that like button if you have
any suggestions for what you want me to
cover and future c++ videos just leave a
comment below you can also port the
series by going over to patreon hopeful
such that show know you'll get some cool
rewards and just helps make sure that I
can keep making these videos as often as
possible for you guys if you want any
more help with see both boss as well the
best place to get it is just to join my
discord at the trailer home slash
discord lots of great people there that
can help you out and we just talk about
programming and stuff like that all day
it's a great time I will see you guys
next time goodbye
[Music]